<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short essay of afflictions, or, Balme to comfort if not cure those that sinke or languish under present misfortunes, and are not prepared in these unsetled times to meet all events with constant and equall tempers written from one of His Majesties garrisons as a private advise to his onely sonne, and by him printed to satisfie the importuniry of some particular friends.</title>
            <author>Monson, John, Sir, 1600-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51172</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32108</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12323936</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12323936</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59507</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51172)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59507)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1017:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short essay of afflictions, or, Balme to comfort if not cure those that sinke or languish under present misfortunes, and are not prepared in these unsetled times to meet all events with constant and equall tempers written from one of His Majesties garrisons as a private advise to his onely sonne, and by him printed to satisfie the importuniry of some particular friends.</title>
                  <author>Monson, John, Sir, 1600-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 126 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.G.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: An essay of afflictions.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Monson by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59507:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59507:1"/>
            <p>A Short ESSAY OF AFFLICTIONS.</p>
            <p>OR, Balme to Comfort if not Cure thoſe that Sinke or Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh under preſent misfortunes, and are not prepared in theſe unſetled times to meet all events, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and equall tempers.</p>
            <p>Written from one of His Majeſties Garriſons, as a private adviſe to his onely Sonne, and by him Printed to ſatisfie the importunity of ſome particular friends.</p>
            <figure/>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke 21.19</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>In your patience poſſeſſe ye your Soules.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Pet. 4.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Let them that ſuffer according to the will of God commit the keeping of their Soules to him in well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as unto a faithfull Creatour.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. G.</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:59507:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59507:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>My deereſt Sonne,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince I know that man is only tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happy, that the want of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things cannot make mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, I cannot but adviſe you to winde up and raiſe your thoughts to higher objects then ſublunary triflles; And when you doe looke upon the low tranſitories of this world, let it be through the wrong, or rather Right end of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians Perſpective, that they may appeare but little, if any thing, in
<pb facs="tcp:59507:3"/>
your eyes, which are ſo weake and empty of all true comfort in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that as Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> upon the devils vaniſhing proſpect <hi>Matthew 4.</hi> ſaith, he ſhewed all in a moment to our Saviour, leaſt looking a little he had ſeene no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; neither doth our Jeſu, who knew beſt the way to hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe in that he was the way, ſet any other eſtimate upon them: for when he commands us to ſeeke a Kingdome, it is of heaven, not earth, omitting the very naming of any thing here below, as of no value, all things temporall being with him but as duſt upon the ballance, or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waights caſt onely into the ſcale, as appendices of grace, and ſo meane as not worthy the name of a gift from him. And this the devill knew ſo well, that in his tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of power, he acknowledged
<pb facs="tcp:59507:3"/>
Chriſt to be the Sonne of God. But, as <hi>Aquinas</hi> obſerves, in that of weakneſſe, wherein he bated his lure onely with the periſhing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things (the ſhadowes, and ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances of glory) the ſole Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy of the world, he conſidered him onely as a man, and durſt not once call him the Sonne of God, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it might prevaile with frayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not Infinitie. From whence let me ingage you to fortifie your ſelfe againſt ſuch allurements. And though you are likely by Gods mercy yet to poſſeſſe a competent meaſure of earthly comforts (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the ſtraites and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties I have paſſed) let not them poſſeſſe you, but be in the world, not of it. And though ſome part of the affections will touch upon it, while you are here, let it be but like a wheele, in Puncto, in the leaſt point, and that not fixt,
<pb facs="tcp:59507:4"/>
but moving, conſidering all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low are but periſhing vanities, good onely (when vertue animates, and ſends them abroad) in their uſing, not injoying, when you muſt be taken from them, if not they from you; and the longeſt terme of having them is but for life; which ever diminiſheth by increaſing, and is at moſt but a bubble, a ſmoake, or ayery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the onely difference, as one ſaith, betweene ſleep, and death that ſoone comes to nothing. Yet this ſhort ſpanne or thread of life is moſt commonly ravelled out, in trouble to get, care to keepe, and feare to looſe theſe unſatisfying comforts, which at no time are permanent, but now, as it were dying at the very root, when ſuch an Inundation of miſery is broken in upon us, as hath almoſt brought all things to another Chaos; ſo
<pb facs="tcp:59507:4"/>
that nothing but an almighty power can bring light out of our darkneſſe; forme, beauty, and order out of ſuch a heape, and maſſe of confuſion. Nay, ſuch is the violent tide, and impetuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſome mens paſſions, as they would doe more then <hi>Noahs</hi> flood, in making but one common grave for State, Church, and all, though God hath in his goodneſſe yet bounded them, in ſaying, <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto you ſhall goe, and no further;</hi> and will ſtill give us ſafety, ſalvation in the Arke, (the true and Ancient Proteſtant faith, &amp; Reverentiall worſhip as it was reformed, and practiſed in Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes) riſe, and rage thoſe waters never ſo much; for God being Pilot, will ſteere, and keep it floating upon thoſe devouring waves, till he finde it another Ararat to reſt on;
<pb facs="tcp:59507:5"/>
yet that you may guide your courſe with the more comfort, and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in this troubled Ocean, J ſhall like a lanterne in the haven, or ſo many Sea-markes for direction commend unto you theſe few pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall conſiderations following; which truly like the ballaſt of the Ship, have kept me in an even and ſafe courſe, in the midſt of our greateſt ſtormes, and made me by Gods infinite goodneſſe happy in miſery, rich in want, and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all conditions: nor will they prove unprofitable to you, if you looke up to God for a bleſſing, when you reflect upon them in your meditations, but will make you in habit, and affections above misfortunes, if not a Martyr, (when called to it upon Chriſtian, and noble termes) and in Calmes tackle, and tite your weake built Pinnace to endure all weathers up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:59507:5"/>
any change. And I feare, though our preſent clouds (the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate meſſengers of tempeſts) doe ſomethtng ſcatter, they may gather again into a higher malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity then ever, ſince I ſee they are ſtill bigge with thoſe foggy and fiery exhalations, out of which the Thunder-bolts of Gods wrath were lately formed, and made; and I feare our new ſinnes will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine midwife, and bring them forth to wrack us in the very ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, if wee allay not the ſtorme by a ſhower of repentant teares, and by our more faithfull ſincere, and conſtant returnes to God, turne his wrath from us (which he of his mercy grant, if it be his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed will,) and how ever inable you, (and all his) to undergoe with an equall temper, and holy ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, what his wiſedome hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:59507:6"/>Onely I ſhall deſire you to uſe theſe ſhort <hi>Eſſayes</hi> piouſly, (the Subject whereof is chiefly the Chriſtians comportment in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions) as a meanes to fix your Quick-ſilver, and unconſtant temper: And I ſhall not doubt but God of his mercy will water this my planting which the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly dew of his grace, and make it bring forth comfort here with joy in the holy Ghoſt; and (with the Phenix) Glory in your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, which is the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your affectionate Father.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Aprill the <hi>20.</hi> An. Do. <hi>1646.<figure/>
                     </hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:59507:6"/>
            <head>AN ESSAY OF AFFLICTIONS, AND The Chriſtian's comport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in them.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the whole life of Chriſt was a continued cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixion, in that he was borne a Martyr, found a Golgatha in <hi>Bethlem,</hi> and made his birth, and his death, his
<pb facs="tcp:59507:7"/>
Chriſtmas, and good Friday, both Morn, and Evening of one and the ſame day of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering; we that fight under the Banner of his Croſſe, muſt not thinke to follow our Generall in his triumphs, if we leave him in the field, or carry no markes of Honour (Prints of his wounds) about us, which how mortall ſoever, never prove deadly; But as <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus</hi> ſaid, when <hi>Aſclehiades</hi> made his tormentors cut and crucifie him, <hi>(Tot ecce laudant ora, quot ſunt vulnera)</hi> muſt prove ſo many mouthes to praiſe, and glorifie God with: and not with <hi>Ionas</hi> be angry though he ſtrike our Gourd, take all worldly comforts from us, and exchange them for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny poſitive evils, eſpecially ſince a heathen <hi>Anaxarchus,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59507:7"/>
when <hi>Nicoreon</hi> a Tyrant would have brayed him in a morter could ſay, (his cauſe being good,) <hi>Thou canſt but beat the Bag, the Sachell, not the man.</hi> Nay ſuch hath beene the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, and courage of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, as <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> ſaid when in expectation of Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack, <hi>the man may periſh, his fortitude cannot.</hi> And therefore let us Chriſtians much more contend with the Ax, grow by cutting, and with Cummin, live by dying; for if they be more then men, ſhall not we be more then they? and with the ball, <hi>percuſſa ſurgo,</hi> ſince with <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the Fable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Sun and the winde, the roughneſſe of the tempeſt made the travellor wrap his cloake about him (keepe what he had) the faſter, when the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59507:8"/>
ſilent Rhetoricke of the ſuns beames overcame him, and made him diveſt himſelfe. Nay, if man that was God, was obſcured, over-ſhadowed, and in ſo inglorious an eſtate as to ſuffer all the degrees, and dimenſions of Shame, Paine, and Death for us; ſhall not we, wormes, and no men, ſuffer our ſelves to be trampled on for him? and think it no ſhame, but our ſecurity to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire into the Caverns (our moſt abject, and ſecluſe beings) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the malice of our Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, when they ſhall ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade us, as not to allow us a viſible one; Eſpecially ſince God will be there both our Priſon,<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.7.</note> Keeper, hiding place, and Preſerver, whether we conſider the Church Dilated, or contracted into one man:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59507:8"/>
ſo that, though our life be a warfare, and the weake built Pinnaces of our bodies are no ſooner lanced out of their ports (our Mothers wombes) into the Ocean of this world,<note place="margin">Job. 7.1.</note> but they are torn, and toſſed by the ſeverall warring bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes of various accidents, If a heavenly winde fill our ſayles (the ſpirit of God breath gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our Prayers) and that our maine maſt hold out a white Flag of Innocency inlayed with the red croſſe of Chriſts blood, conſcience being our Pilot, the Scriptures our compaſſe, his Promiſes our Anchor, and our Pole-ſtar Chriſt, in Shipwrack we ſhall have a Planke, in the ſea a Whale to preſerve us, and waft us into a more ſafe, if not ſo calme a harbour, as we
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59507:9"/>
aymed at. For though God ſubmits his Children to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to, and ſenſible of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, as the common conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of man, he will then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them from the venome, though not the ſting of thoſe vipers; and if toſſed with ſtormes, will put a ſtrong Ship under them, and make the lowdeſt thunder, but as a lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty voyce, or lowd Muſicke to uſher in their triumph, and Coronation; And if he ſuffer them to be troden into the earth with ſcornes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, it is but (as Seed is bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed to make it multiply the more) that they might riſe the more glorious, which ſhould encourage us to endeavour to make all events equall to us, knowing that like the beſt ſteele we may (by the grace of
<pb facs="tcp:59507:9"/>
God) faſhion them either into a ſheild or ſword to our ſelves Proſperity and Adverſity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but the matter, the ſtamp or forme ours to give, either the Lions fierceneſſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive nature, or the Lambs Innocence. For the moſt rough, and hard afflictions are in themſelves, as all things of indifferencie, neither Good, nor Bad, but in order to their laſt end; So as Croſſes (as they are Corrections for, and not ſimply Puniſhments of our ſinnes) may become mercies, and bleſſings unto us, and are a part of divine providence both in reſpect of their Author,<note place="margin">Amos 3. Eſ. 45. Lam. 3. Heb. 12.</note> Order and End, when it is his wiſdome to advance our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe by ſufferings, that no Perſon of the meaneſt conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might miſſe of a meanes to
<pb facs="tcp:59507:10"/>
felicity. And ſo to be not onely patiently and cheerfully ſubmitted to,<note place="margin">Luk. 6.28</note> but rejoyced in. If we ſuffer for righteouſneſſe ſake,<note n="*" place="margin">Jam. 1.2.</note> and look to God as the Creator, and Conductor of them.<note n="*" place="margin">1 Peter 2.</note> For when we ſee the Puppits move (the men of this world bite, and wound us) we muſt conſider an inviſible hand moving the wiers, ordering the Events for his own glory, and our ſalvation; And in this ſence, though afflictions are the onely ſure inheritance of Humanity,<note n="*" place="margin">Job. 5.</note> (whoſe income is Teares, his rent for life, Cares, and Feares: his outgoings, horrour and trouble in the force of natures diſſolution) they are more peculiarly the Portion of the righteous,<note n="*" place="margin">Lam. 3. Heb. 12. Amos. 3.</note> who like a ſquare die will ſtand firme though caſt upon any
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59507:10"/>
chance, (which made <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> ſay; an honeſt man was a ſquare man, one that would be himſelfe in all conditions) and as a well built Arch will ſtand the faſter, by addition of waite, and burden, or with the Center in the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be fixt with <hi>Iob,</hi> though all worldly things move in their viciſſitudes, and ſeverall changes to evill about him: knowing he that wounds will heale, and not onely in famine redeem from death, in warre from the power of the ſword, but will ſet him above misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and make them all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient to his good,<note n="*" place="margin">Job. 5.</note> turning the Serpent of afflictions with <hi>Aarons</hi> into a Rod budding new, and freſh joyes, and teach him Salamander like, to live in flames, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59507:11"/>
all events with evenneſſe, and patience, knowing that the ſtrongeſt windes, if he ſayle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, will but convey him to Chriſt, who commands the windes and Seas, and they o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey. But the better to prop, and ſupport our weake, and tottering reſolutions, I will raiſe ſome pillars of comfort to reſt upon, if we looke after and follow the examples both of Chriſt,<note n="*" place="margin">Eſ. 53. Pſa. 18.</note> whoſe Cratch was a Crucifixion; his whole life one continued Paſſion; and all the holy men of God,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>Chr. 21.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. 1.21.2.20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sam. 3.18 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sam. 18.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6. Eſay 39.8. Micha 7.9. Ro. 5.13.</note> who found no other way to heaven then that of thornes; and bare all the waight of miſery, that was laid upon them, as if they felt it no more, then thoſe that live in the circle of the Ayre, and yet finde no pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derouſneſſe in it, becauſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59507:11"/>
is heavy in its own ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that croſſes, and loſſes being the matter, and Principle as it were out of which a Chriſtian is formed, cannot make him ſinke under the preſſure of them; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, if we conſider the two chiefe ends for which they are ſent, Gods glory, mans ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and every way Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
            <p>Firſt, afflictions are ſent ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> times for Gods glory; not as puniſhments for our ſinnes, though they are alwayes the meritorious and occaſionall cauſe of judgements. Thus the blinde man in the Goſpell wanted his ſight,<note n="*" place="margin">Jo. 9.2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> (and with <hi>Tobias</hi> recovered it by this gaul of afflictions) that we might ſee the power, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God in his deliverance
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59507:12"/>
both from corporall and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall blindneſſe; for as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries are the beſt Comments upon one another; ſo Gods Goodneſſe, and Greatneſſe moſt appeares in bringing health out of Sickneſſe, Light out of Darkneſſe, and forming all the well ordered, and vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous beauties of the world out of nothing, or a Chaos, and great Maſſe of confuſion; hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe out of miſery, glory out of ſufferings, giving victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in thraldome, and triumph to his when conquered, as the true trophies of Chriſtian mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naminitie, and moſt legible Characters of his favour to his Church, which with the buſh is ever burning,<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 3.2</note> yet never to be conſumed; &amp; like the Arke however floating upon the proud imperious high ſwelling
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59507:12"/>
waves, ſinkes not, but when threatned to be involved in the whole worlds generall deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, having but one common winding-Sheet (the pleated waters) and as it were one common buriall place, then is preſerved, and by thoſe wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry riſing mountaines but lifted up the neerer heaven, God as it were like another Neptune imbarking himſelfe in (and hazarding Shipwrack with) his Church.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they are ſent <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> for our ſalvation, not as a cauſe of, but way to glory; as they are a meanes of our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe here <hi>(in that whoſoever will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus muſt ſuffer afflictions)</hi> and happineſſe hereafter;<note n="*" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.12.</note> there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no way to aſcend the mount of honour but by the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59507:13"/>
ſteps of vertue through a rough, and difficult path; no Haven to be gained unleſſe we paſſe the ſtraits; no way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven but by the gates of hell; for unleſſe we fill up the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Chriſt in his body the Church, and beare his croſſe we cannot be partakers of his Crown, induring being the condition of Reigning with him.<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 14.22. Coloſ. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tim. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pſ. 73.4.</note> In that his firſt inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when he deſtroyes, is to Preſerve us, which is the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>the wicked have no bands in their death, receive not their puniſhment here.</hi> And who would not upon theſe terms loſe a life to ſave it, who may by ſaving loſe it? nay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what Marchant would not to recover his wiſhed haven with a wealthy lading be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to have his veſſell wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59507:13"/>
beaten, and torne? and much more a Chriſtian, that is a man of warre; a Barke built for all weathers, ſtormes, and Calmes, knowing that the rough Sea proves the Pilot, and makes him keep at the ſterne and helme, uſing all holy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devours to avoid every Rock, and Sand of Temptation, and ply the pumpe upon the leaſt leake, knowing that the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt ſinne unrepented, neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or not with <hi>Jonas</hi> throwne over-bord to appeaſe the ſtorme, will ſinke the talleſt veſſell, and better unlade all then the man ſhould periſh. Nay, ſhall our Lord, Head, and Generall be all wounded, torn, and expoſed to all degrees of ſuffering for us, and ſhall not we (his Church, and members) undergoe ſome troubles, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59507:14"/>
a ſcratch, or weare a ſcarre for him? ſhall hee drinke up the full Cup, and ſhowres of his Fathers wrath, and ſhall not wee taſte of thoſe few remaining drops for him? ſhall innocence ſuffer, and guilt goe free? nay, ſhall God dye for man, and man undergoe no preſſure for God? nay, for himſelfe, his own advantage, where diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſectings are recompactings; God forbid. No, away with ſuch puſillanimity, my ſoule, and leave not thy Saviour in his ſufferings for thee. Though thou art called with <hi>Simon</hi> of <hi>Cyrene</hi> to take up his Croſſe (or rather thine,<note n="*" place="margin">Iſay. 53.</note> which he bore for thee) and beare it for him, till thou comeſt to Golgatha, the place of Sculs, (thy grave) nay, further, if
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59507:14"/>
poſſible. For as a devoute man ſaid, if he could finde or apprehend any defect of joy in heaven, it would be onely in that he could not there ſuffer for his Saviour. Though what we undergoe here is not more for his glory, then our bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. And therefore as Muſick is ſweeteſt, when expiring, let the laſt ſwanlike Act of our ſufferings be but harmoniouſly accordant to Chriſt in that ſweet ditty of his, <hi>not mine, but thy will be done.</hi> And a Raviſhment of delight will ſo poſſeſſe our ſoules, as we ſhall onely account our life from our Death, and that our birth day to Eternity, Our eve or vigil to our great feſtivall at the marriage of the Lambe; for as God moved upon the waters in the Creation, before
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59507:15"/>
they brought forth the firſt Creature, ſo afflictions are now thoſe many waters, in which God moves to make us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in our hearts by the holy Ghoſt, like the wombe of the virgine, till Chriſt be formed in us, and we bring forth holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which he ever crownes with happineſſe. Now though theſe are the firſt, Primary, and Principall ends, why Gods children are thus brought forth with labour, &amp; ſorrow (a curſe as ancient as ſin it ſelfe) there are many other practicall uſes, and pious conſiderations we ſhould entertaine them with; for as one ſaith, <hi>Schola crueis eſt ſchola lucis; and Oratio, Lectio, temptatio,</hi> the rough, but ready way to Heaven, and the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled waters of Repentant teares the cleereſt Perſpective
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59507:15"/>
in an Eclipſe of Gods favour to ſee his face ſhine in our devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which uſually riſe, and fall with the waves of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the greateſt miſery ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily making us moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate for mercy (as one depth calling upon another) and moſt carefull of our wayes. Like the Horſe that ever goeth ſureſt, and beſt when he feeles the ſpurre, and bridle the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riner that moſt uſeth his plum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, and compaſſe in ſtormes. And thus we will conſider af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, as they are incentives <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> to Prayer, and like fire extract the beſt incenſe of our devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, making them to aſcend in a holy flame of zeale to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate our peace, and pacifie an exaſperated Deity, whoſe Power, Juſtice, and Mercy are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59507:16"/>
all ingaged to deliver them, that in afflictions call upon him.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 30.34 107. Hoſ. 5 Eſay 49.3. Lam. 3.</note>For then we doe their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand, and cannot miſſe of a Gracious Audience no more then <hi>Abraham,</hi> where Duſt and Aſhes pleaded with his maker, and as it were ſo charmed his eare with this Oratory, that importunity it ſelfe could not weary him.<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 18.</note> Nay with this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Ingine, Impotence and weakneſſe overcomes Power and Omnipotence, puts mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles upon the hands of God: and (with an humble reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be it ſpoken) worſts him in the conflict, making him cry out, <hi>Let me alone,</hi> or <hi>till thou art gone, I can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 32. Numb. 14.</note> as to <hi>Moſes.</hi> Thus a faithfull Prayer workes all kinds of miracles, makes the Heavens, Earth, and Seas obey.
<pb facs="tcp:59507:16"/>
For when the gaſping Earth is dying for Thirſt, <hi>Elias</hi> can by Prayer quicken and enliven it. It can fix the Sunne in the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, as in a Center, give Eares to the Grave, and make them open, and life to the dead;<note place="margin">Jo. 12.</note> And ever neſts a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, (like a Dove in the clifts of the Rock,) in the wounds of his Saviour, ſo as he cannot when aſſaulted, be ſenſible of any Dangers, but reſts ſecure in ſtormes: whereas the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mans Proſperity is but like the winter Sun-ſhine, late up, and all wayes ſetting in thick clouds, and like the bird <hi>Cige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Suidas</hi> ſpeakes of, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes dies in the act of fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering. And therefore with <hi>Moſes,</hi> let us rather chuſe to ſuffer afflictions with the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God then to injoy the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59507:17"/>
pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon: knowing, that the moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured, and benighted Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an can by the gentle breath of a fervent Prayer, or the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and more contracted winds of ſighes, and Groanes diſperſe thoſe thick vapours that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe his happineſſe, inlighten that Darkeneſſe and uſhers in a moſt bright, glorious, and cheerfull morning. So the Prophet <hi>David, Heavineſſe may endure for a night, but Ioy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with the breake of day,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 30.</note> when we are ſaluted with the beames of the riſing Sunne of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe in our ſoules;<note place="margin">Iſ. 54.1.8.</note> Onely let us obſerve this, that (though in ſome waters the leaſt ſayle makes moſt ſpeed) in theſe Seas all ſayles muſt be hoyſed, all the affections ſtirring, though a Penitents loudeſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59507:17"/>
voyce in his eye full of teares (not his tongue full of words) if God blow upon thoſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and make them flow. And therefore one ſaith well, Teares in Prayer, or the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Teares are the blotting out of the hand-writing, that is againſt us, (as a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous meanes, no meritorious cauſe) and the <hi>uſury</hi> by which the joyes of heaven are multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to us; Gods free pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting Grace in the applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the blood of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Stock, and Principle. Thus afflictions alarum Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and Prayer routs and van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſheth afflictions. It is a <hi>Moſes</hi> in the gap, an <hi>Elias,</hi> the Chariots and Horſemen of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, by which we conquer.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Afflictions are to be entertained with delight
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59507:18"/>
(ſoe Saint <hi>Iames</hi>) as they work every way for our good,<note n="*" place="margin">James 1.2.</note> and make Gods anger his Love to us; which made <hi>David</hi> cry out,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſa. 119.71.</note> 
               <hi>It is good for me that I have beene afflicted, and taught thy Lawes;</hi> and teach us by many other expreſſions, what <hi>Lemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> ſaith, <hi>noſtrae ſalutis avidus,</hi> God is moſt endevouring to love us, when he moſt corrects us, and ſends Croſſes like his meſſengers in the Goſpell to compell thoſe that neglect his Invitation, and to draw them by force to the meanes of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; his Love, Patience, and long ſuffering brings not in to him,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 6.126.6.</note> ever making the matter of a good mans ſorrow the cauſe of his rejoycing;<note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 31.16.</note> for Afflictions no ſooner ſtirre up to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance (as in <hi>Ephraim</hi>) but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance bringeth Reprive,
<pb facs="tcp:59507:18"/>
and Pardon,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> by a refined Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimy turning all things into good for us, and extracting the moſt Soveraigne Cordials out of the rankeſt poyſons, the beſt Mithridate from the moſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous ſcorpions, ever making the Lilly amongſt the Thornes (the Embleme of the Church) retaine its whiteneſſe, her Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Innocence, however ſcratched and torne, ſtill ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering beauty from her skars, and with the Roſe ſweetneſſe, when it hangs amongſt the Briars, but withering, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating of its Odours, if once pulled from them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as they are a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> meanes of our Perſeverance in that they doe not onely call us home, but keep us ſteddy in our returne to it; and if we ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſlack in, or deviate from
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59507:19"/>
our way in Piety, like the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders hand, and heele, they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times reſtraine our wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings, and quicken us in our pace and progreſſe towards heaven, and as the Teather of the ſoule, bounds, and confines us, when our untamed diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions would furiouſly breake forth into many Extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, God many times curing us by Contraries; Sodoms fulnes of bread by Egypts famine; <hi>hedging</hi> us in a narrow &amp; ſtraite path with Thornes to walk in, when we would perhaps lay all waſte before us that ſtands in oppoſition to our propoſed ends, deſtroy Propriety, and not onely uſurpe upon others intereſts, and ruine our owne, but invade God in his (the too much I feare practiſed ſinne of theſe dayes) Onely the Princes
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59507:19"/>
of <hi>Iuda,</hi> will not, I hope, be like thoſe that would remove the bounds,<note n="*" place="margin">Hoſ. 5.10, 11.</note> both Civill with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the State, the fence of common intereſt, morall bounds, the ſquare, and Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of our obedience, and Characters of Pure Nature, or Evangelicall (both Practicall, and Contemplative) by which we are to faſhion, and order our ſelves in the worſhip of God, the inward, and outward man, thoughts, actions, and devotions, not onely acting, but enacting miſchiefe, as a Law;<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 9 48</note> thus the brighteſt day, if the Sunne ſet in a cloud, will looſe its Garland; our Ripeſt beginnings without ſutable proceedings prove fruitles; our beſt appearances but Ciphers, which how capacious ſoever in the figure, and taking up the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59507:20"/>
greateſt roomes, with God ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie nothing. But if when falling, God lend us his hand, by Afflictions cauſe our Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, Our Perſeverance in Goodneſſe (in quick, and ſharp trials) as one of the blood Royall, and immediate heires of Gods Kingdome, crownes our Afflictions, and drawes that oyle of Gladneſſe out of thoſe flints, if we are not cowardly jealous, in ſuſpecting what we moſt deſire, but by Faith rely upon Gods promiſe for it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, Afflictions are to be borne as they come from the hand of a Father,<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 3.19</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 3.11.12.</note> with bowels and Compaſſion, more of Love then Anger, to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, not Puniſh us. And if neceſſity,<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 18</note> which is alwayes an ill Companion (many times, a bad Counſellor) doth at any
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59507:20"/>
time, with the Prodigall make us returne to our Father with a modeſt baſhfulneſſe, and humble confeſſion of our ſins, our Remembring them, will make him forget them; Our ſhaming our ſelves will be his Juſtification of us: neither will God expect our Return, but accepts the Reſolution for the Performance. For no ſooner did this loſt Sonne purpoſe to goe back to his Father, but He goes forth of himſelfe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent him with kindneſſe, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking as it were his Greatneſſe in a Gratious Condeſcent to meet and embrace him: and like a carefull nurſe never ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers him to fall againe, but to teach him the better to ſtand, and looke to his footing, never layes the Rod upon him, but (as we doe a whip upon a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59507:21"/>
Toppe) to make him goe the better for being well ſcourged,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 34.50. Jſ. 21.54.</note> and layes his Corraſives to his dead fleſh, not that he delights in his Paine, but intends his Cure.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, we ought to beare Afflictions cheerefu ly and Thankfully, if we conſider how much our ſinnes deſerve,<note n="*" place="margin">Eſ. 59.</note> and with what a gentle hand we are puniſhed,<note n="*" place="margin">Ez. 3.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Lam. 3.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> God ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding beyond our merits, correcting much leſſe then our Iniquities challenge from his Juſtice; in that he delights to ſhew mercy, and is alwayes unwilling to inflict Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 46.27, 28.</note> (but calling it his <hi>ſtrange worke,</hi> as it were declines it,) nor ſtrikes at all, but in mercy (and that his greateſt, in that he is then ſaid to goe out of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe) ever with <hi>Jonathan</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:59507:21"/>
ſhouting his Arrows to warne, not wound us, never Purging, Lancing, nor Cutting, but for our health, and Recovery. Nay he is ſo ſlow to puniſh, as that he calls Afflictions the <hi>vials of his wrath</hi> from their ſhape, and ſtraitnes;<note n="*" place="margin">Lam. 3.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 23</note> to ſhew how hardly he pours them out upon us, and never but in meaſure, having his ſtaffe to ſupport, as well as his Rod to humble us, his Cork as well as his lead, when he ſinkes us to keepe us floating, ſo as we cannot be drown'd, Chriſt our head be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing above water. And God to aſſure us the more of a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py iſſue to every temptation<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.13.</note> (if we waite upon him in the way of his judgements, and judge our ſelves to prevent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing further judged) will as he hath promiſed, make the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59507:22"/>
looſe their natures, and be our Protectors, not Executioners. <hi>For when we walke through the fire, it ſhall not burne us, and when we goe through the waters, they ſhall not over-flow us;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſ. 43.2.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iſ. 26.8.</note> But the<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.31.</note> fiued waters ſhall become a hard Pavement to our feet (as to Chriſts upon the Sea) and the fiery furnace a ſafe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tiring place, againſt our Enemies; for God is alwayes tipping his ſpeare with hony, like <hi>Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans,</hi> to refreſh as well as wound us.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, Afflictions are ſent to teach us Humility, the beſt Dreſſe, and Ornament of a vertuous ſoule, and to correct the high-towring vapour of Pride. Thus <hi>David,</hi> that thought in his Proſperity <hi>hee ſhould never be removed,</hi> in Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59507:22"/>
could acknowledge it was God <hi>that made his moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſo ſtrong:</hi> which was the Reaſon alſo that Saint <hi>Pauls Thorne in his fleſh</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 12</note> was not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, to bring him to the knowledge of the Rock out of which he was hewen, to remember what he was in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 103</note> and in foundation but duſt: that with the Peacock all his high creſted vanities, and richeſt plume of Graces inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, looking to his feet, his icy, ſlippery, and fraile bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, might not make him proud, but ſtanding by Gods Grace onely he might ſtill fear to fall, falling from that feare being the undermining of the whole frame, In that the higheſt and firmeſt buildings are alwayes raiſed from the loweſt foundations; And the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59507:23"/>
moſt improved Chriſtian ever appearing like a <hi>Pyramis</hi> (the higher it's built) the leſſe, and leſſe in his owne eyes (though as one obſerves well, Pride is natures ſhirt, that ſticks cloſeſt to him, and he puts off laſt) ever ſaying with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in his viſions, Revelations, and unexampled Piety, <hi>It is not I, but the Grace of God in me.</hi> Thus with the heathen <hi>Pliny</hi> to <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> we may ſay, Afflictions bring us home to our ſelves; ſo that if we could but performe in Proſperity, what we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe in Adverſity, we ſhould be living Saints, not Proud ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Doing Juſtly, loving mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and walking humbly with our God.<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 1. 1 King. 8. Mich 6.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, we are to endure Afflictions, as they fit and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our ſoyl for better fruits,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59507:23"/>
and make us abound in Piety, and Good works;<note n="*" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.12. Eccleſ.</note> God by an Egyptian midwife many times bringeth forth a true Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralite, and by pruning his vine,<note place="margin">2 Hoſ. 5.15.</note> beating his ſpices, correcting his ſervants makes their fruits and Graces more full, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant and diffuſive.<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 119 7 55.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Jo. 10.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 5.</note> For like the good husbandman, that plowes, and harrowes his ground, to make it bring forth the fuller harveſt, that cudgels, and threſheth his walnut tree to make it <hi>Teeme</hi> and <hi>Layde</hi> its bowes, God alſo ſtudies all wayes to improve our Graces, and his owne Glory, ever ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a winter before a ſpring, froſts and ſnow to ſoften and mellow the mould of our Earthly hearts,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 32.34.</note> the better to prepare us for his good ſeed, and a Rich returne, though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59507:24"/>
we doe in that but gather, and carry in for our ſelves, when in crowning us hee crownes but his own worke in us:<note place="margin">Iſ. 54. Math. 26.39.</note> firſt making us beare his Croſſe, and then weare his Garland, all afflictions being but as the Cloud and Pillar of fire before the Iſraelites, to protect, not deſtroy us, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend us from our Enemies and lead us over <hi>Iordan</hi> to our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed land, Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Eightly, we may be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to undergoe Afflictions here, becauſe they are not du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, though weighty, in that Chriſts Prayer hath made this Cup paſſant; So as the ſtormes of Afflictions, when they thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en moſt upon us, are not ſtayed but moving, nay, flying away upon the wings of the winde, never enduring above a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59507:24"/>
in the <hi>Ephemerides</hi> of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence,<note n="*" place="margin">Iſ. 55.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſa. 31.34.</note> however te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious if we meaſure them by our meaſures of Time (Clocks, and dialls;) nay not a minute or expence of the leaſt graine of Sand, if computed by the glaſſe of Eternity, (which is ever running, but never waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) or the immenſe duration of the rewards, when Faith, Repentance, and all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellations of other Graces in us, ſhall like the hand upon the Diall, Point at, nay, ſhew the Meridian, Declining and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod of our day of Affliction, and that afternoone halfe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity of happineſſe we are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be poſſeſſed of; for with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> Our troubles here are for continuance nothing,<note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor 4.17.</note> or the leaſt part of Time, but a Moment, for weight light, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59507:25"/>
the moſt ponderous but a fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſcales with more exceeding, nay Eternall, nay Eternall waight nay Eternall waight of Glory, Glory for ſhame, waighty for light, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity of injoying for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary ſuffering;<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 7.14</note> and therefore though a perplexed fancy diſturbing the Organs of Reaſon may like a falſe glaſſe multiply our troubles, and dangers, let us with a ſteddy faith behold them in their own Dimenſions, finite in reſpect both of their meaſure and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, And we ſhall ſoone be brought to ſay with Saint <hi>Paul, I have fought a good fight, J have finiſhed my courſe,</hi> and <hi>now there is laid up for me a Crowne of glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ninthly, Afflictions are to be welcomed, as they are
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59507:25"/>
ſeales of our Adoption, Badges of our Profeſſion, Earneſts of Grace, and beginnings of Glory.<note n="*" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.11.12. Job. 5. Math. 10.16.14. Heb. 12.</note> The Red Sea, through which we much paſſe to the Land of Canaan, the Crowne of Thornes we muſt weare here, if we will have one of Gold with Chriſt in heaven.<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.13. Matth. 5.20.</note> The onely Thiſtles, from which we may gather Figgs, and Briers, that yeeld grapes for wine to cheere the the heart, being once ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with all might, according to his glorious Power, with all Patience, and long ſuffering with joyfulneſſe.<note n="*" place="margin">Coloſ. 1.</note> For with the Roman Orators, as he lives not that hath onely the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this life in his thoughts, ſo he never dyeth, nor is ever ſenſible of temporary troubles, that can caſt them up rightly,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59507:26"/>
and be willing to change a houſe of clay, a Breath, or va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour of ſmoke, a Body of Death, and garment of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption for Immortality, and honour; a Region of Death for the land of the living; the life of man for that of Angels; a vally of Teares for a mount of Joy.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Tenthly, conſider that God layes his Afflictions upon us, in regard of his Propriety in us, Making that the ground of his care over us;<note n="*" place="margin">Iſay. 51. Ezek. 34 11.15.</note> Thus he weeds his Garden, dreſſeth, and fence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Vineyard with Briars, and Thornes, both to defend, and make it fruitfull, ſhakes his Trees that the Rotten fruit might fall off, and they take the better rooting, It being the higheſt end, and chiefeſt fruit of Afflictions to take away ſin,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59507:26"/>
and preſerve the ſinner, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the worme and cancer, that would otherwiſe deſtroy the Tree; many times to give it ſhade, leaſt too much ſunne ſhould dry and wither it; or like that in the early ſpring produce many gay flowers and odoriferous ſmels to court the ſenſes, but withall ingender millions of flyes, and vermine, to ſpoile them; for ſo the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this world are but a <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> gourd, ſumer fruit, of ſhort continuance, wheras the winter fruits, that indure moſt of cold and nipping froſts, are for du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and laſting. Thus though great miſts doe ever midwife in Calmes; the Ayre is then moſt tainted, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, whereas thunder brings forth a moſt whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, pure, ſerene and bright
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59507:27"/>
skie. Nay, Afflictions makes us every way better in our ſpirituall condition, and fit to be owned by the Father of ſpirits, who like a cunning I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidary tries his Jewels before he gives them a Rich ſetting, that if true, not Counterfeit, <hi>he might ſpare them,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Malach. 3 17.</note> 
               <hi>as a man ſpareth his onely Sonne;</hi> nay, they are Gods bullets ſhot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an Armour of proofe, to trie, not peirce it; there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more ſtrength in the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of his Saints, then in all Goliahs Braſſe and Irons, that he might treaſure it up in his Militia for the honour of his Saints, and beautifying of his owne habitation.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Eleventhly, Afflictions are Gods love tokens to us, the Dialect in which he woes us, and true Anagram of our ſins,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59507:27"/>
(in that we may uſually read our ſinnes, and faylings in the ſpecification of his judgements upon us) by them to make us conſider the deformity of all other objects, and unite our affections in him; the rather when we ſee all the Darling delights of this world ſo ſoone overſhadowed; and alwayes tempered with the bitterneſſe of ſome temporary croſſe, to diſrelliſh our taſte, and abate our Appetite to them; ſo as the reſt of our bodies, many times proves our minds exerciſe; and our empty houres, moſt fill us with vaine and vexings thoughts; at beſt affording us but leſſe paine, no abſolute freedome from troubles, in our moſt retired retirements; for when the doores of our ſenſes are lockt up, the Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59507:28"/>
doth many times <hi>affright us with viſions and terrifie us with dreames,</hi> Job. 7.14. making our waking Conſciences, often Alarum our ſleepy ſoules, by all this reſtleſneſſe to bring us to an everlaſting reſt; and ſhall we neglect his bounty, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive with a wrinckled brow what he gives us with a ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and gracious aſpect? <hi>for to you it is given, not onely to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, but to ſuffer for Chriſt.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ph. 1.29</note> And ſhall we refuſe to weare his favours, livery, and Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance (though a croſſe) that are thus effects of his affection to us and ſo not only in their ſpring but ſtreame; In that his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſo ſteers the action, and orders the event in all things, as a ſparrow fals not without his leave, nor can the devill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a ſwine (ſo little is the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59507:28"/>
largeſt empire here) without his permiſſion,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> and makes all the variety of Accidents (how contrary ſoever the lines are drawne) to center in our good; ſo communicative of himſelfe is his goodneſſe to us. And therefore let not the clay di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute with the Potter, walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brickle earth with the God of heaven. For his actions are alwayes juſt, and good; nay full of mercy to us, though harſh; his Phyſick wholſome, though unpleaſant, in that ſometimes his greateſt mercy, is not to ſhew mercy,<note n="*" place="margin">Hoſ. 4.13 14.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iſai. 1.5. Lam. 1. Wiſd. 12.1.</note> not with-hold the lance, when it is to open an impoſtumation. And therefore, correct me O Lord to amend me, wound me to heale me, kill me to make me live, take away all to give me thy ſelfe. And doe not
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59507:29"/>
hate me ſo much,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ 81.11, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 22.11. Oſ. 15. Ez. 24.13.</note> as not to ſeem to hate me at all, when it is the greateſt puniſhment not to be puniſhed, and the greateſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of our wealth to loſe it, and our live: too for Chriſt,<note n="*" place="margin">Mar. 10.29.30.</note> where the intereſt he payes is ſo great, the Returne ſo infinite we receive here with perſecutions;<note n="†" place="margin">Matth. 10. Act. 14.22.</note> and ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe and unexhauſtible in the world to come;<note n="*" place="margin">Job. 5.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 11 31.</note> for ſo the Apoſtle, <hi>Eye hath not ſeene</hi> (yet the eye is a nimble ſayler, and hath travelled farre, and ſeene much) <hi>eare hath not heard</hi> (yet the eare hath heard more then the eye hath ſeene, being as it were the Portall, or gate of the ſoule, by which know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge enters, and ſo appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends more of the beauties, and Beatitudes of that place then can by all the other ſences be
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59507:29"/>
diſcerned here, in the dim and opake glaſſe of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, though God is here ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry legible in many of his Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes) <hi>nor hath it entered into the thought of man, the joyes that ſhall be revealed</hi> (yet thought hath a kinde of infinity in it, and graſpes more at once, then either eye, or eare can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſurate with the largeſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended faculties, and moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded dimenſions of their ſeverall wayes of comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and diſcerning) having the winges, and motion of a ſpirit, the capacity of an intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, yet ſtill ſhort of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining, the vaſt incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſibleneſſe of that which paſſeth Imagination; For ſuch is Heaven, a circle within a circle, many infolded myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious joyes, which will be
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59507:30"/>
beſt conceived by thinking what we cannot conceive; and becauſe it cannot enter into us here, let us expect with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, till we enter into it here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, and heare with comfort that bleſſed voice of <hi>come ye bleſſed of my Father, &amp; go into the Ioy that is prepared for you from the begining of the world;</hi> And not onely ſo, <hi>but enter into thy Maſters joy</hi> nor onely that, that <hi>is prepared of God for them that love him,</hi> but that which is God, the beatificall viſion it ſelfe. Yet here the Saints of God ſee the dawning of that day, a light ſpringing out of darkneſſe,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 112.4.</note> and beames of comfort in the blackeſt night of Affliction, ſome love glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the moſt unkinde di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce, which is never long, though it ſeemes long to us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:59507:30"/>Twelfthly, Afflictions are <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> ſent, as trials from God, and a meanes of evidencing to our ſelves the truth of our faith, by the exerciſe of it: (as it is the <hi>aſſurance of things hoped for, the evidence of things</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Peter. 1 Iſai. 40.31.</note> not ſeen) which made <hi>Abraham</hi> rely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Promiſe, not diſputing the meanes of its performance, knowing that <hi>Phoenix</hi> like God could raiſe him up a ſeed from the dead aſhes of his <hi>Iſaac;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 22.</note> though in him he offered the comfort of his life, the ſtaffe of his age, the ſumme and Reca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulation of all his numerous poſterity: poſſeſſing as it were future Joyes, and by them was made unſenſible of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent troubles, or at leaſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding them, but endured that <hi>Croſſe, deſpiſed the ſhame, looking unto Jeſus, the finiſher
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59507:31"/>
as well as the author of his faith,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 12.2.</note> the comfortable beames of the ſunne of righteouſneſſe ſtill beating upon his ſoule in their ſtrongeſt reflex, in the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt clouded night of Temptation, which can never be hindered by the ſtormy windes, becauſe Celeſtiall; for true Faith becomes the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er by difficulties, ever prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Croſſe of Chriſt to the Triumphes of Emperours, and all the Crownes of Kings, and with certaine fiſhes mentioned by <hi>Pliny,</hi> is ever ſwimming againſt the ſtreame, to recover the fountaine Chriſt, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that all Refreſhments are originally and virtually there; and with the needle in the mariners compaſſe is fixt, &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable in the greateſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, becauſe not governed by
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59507:31"/>
the turbulent, and unconſtant winds, but the unchangeable Heavens, and never count it any victory to trample upon a worme (any ſmall triall) or to wade through a ſhallow River, but grapples with and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the greateſt oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, knowing Croſſes cannot be ſo large as to out-circle their Crownes. Neither is this all, for faith can here make ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent things preſent, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, when conquered: and though humane friendſhip is like Quick-ſilver ſoone incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porating with the beſt mettles, but in difficulties and the fire conveyes it ſelfe away: faith then knowes divine helpe to be moſt preſent, having the Angels for her Corps de Guard, and God his Pavilion round about her. Nay, in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59507:32"/>
that fire, as with <hi>Moſes</hi> in the buſh (a ſtrange pallace for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity to inthrone in) rather then his ſhall want a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; for if his people be in Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, or that <hi>Aſhur</hi> afflicts them without a cauſe, they truſting in him in their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, God will not be kept above in heaven without a<note n="*" place="margin">Iſ. 52.4.5.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 46.6.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 46.1</note> 
               <hi>what doe I here?</hi> And <hi>I will goe down,</hi> (O the exalted humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our God) to <hi>be their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent helpe in trouble.</hi> Their help in, (not alwayes their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from) trouble. In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>durance their companion, making their priſon their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the perſecutors Chaines,<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 39.21.</note> their Bracelets, and Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments the Lyons, their Guardians, not deſtroyers, as to <hi>Daniel.</hi> In that God, and a Chriſtian are but one in their
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59507:32"/>
ſufferings,<note n="†" place="margin">Jſ. 63.9.</note> * <hi>for I am afflicted in their afflictions,</hi> ſaith he; and they that perſecute us, perſecute our Jeſus in us, (as in Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) who will be ſure to releive us in our neceſſities, (having ingaged all his Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes for it) and make our al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt emptied Curſe a never to be exhauſted ſpring, the Ravens our Caterers, and fiſhes to bring mony in their mouthes to pay our ordinary, rather then we ſhould want to defray our charges, (as in the caſe of Tribute) nay, rather then the faithfull ſhould ſuffer to deſtruction, (his Church which ſhould appeare like an Army well ordered with ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners both for beauty, and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror) God himſelfe will in their march to Canaan be both Harbinger, Quarter-maſter,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59507:33"/>
Generall, and Sutler to the Campe, making the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe a downe bed, the Rocke a Seller, &amp; the heavens a larder to afford them all neceſſaries; Nay, he will beyond it feed them to delight, even with Quailes, and Manna, ſatisfying them as he did <hi>David</hi> in his moſt naked and abject condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And as a Banquet to his meat before the cloth be taken away, and theſe outward things fail) he wil give us Chriſt and in him; a full taſte of his mercies, the onely ſtore-houſe, and true Magazine, nay, the abſtract, and Epitome of all the treaſures both of heaven, and earth; and higher I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſoare in this meditation. For if he ſpare not his ſonne, but deliver him up, not onely for, but to us, <hi>ſhall he not with
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59507:33"/>
him freely give us all things?</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 8.32. Jo. 6</note> as the Apoſtle argues; all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries here, and laſting joyes hereafter, but taking downe our earthen Cottages to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>build them ſtately Palaces, making every graine of duſt ſpring innumerous freſh glories to us.</p>
            <p>Thirteenthly, Afflictions <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> are ſent, for the exerciſe of our charities in ſuffering with, cenſuring of, and giving ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of a holy ſubmiſſion to others.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In ſuffering with others, compaſſion being Paſſion at at the rebound, for <hi>who is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, and I burne, or ſuffer not</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul?</hi> Nay this fire ſoftens our natures, makes them more pliable, malliable, and eaſie to take impreſſions from others ſufferings, and ſo
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59507:34"/>
compaſſionate as to make their miſeries our unhappineſſe, as if one ſoule did animate divers bodies, and we live, and dye in one another, as it was in the Apoſtles times, which is the true box of Spicknard in the Canticles Chriſt powreth out to comfort, and refreſh his ſpouſe with, when neareſt fainting under the croſſe, in that their ſufferings are his Crucifixions.<note n="*" place="margin">Jſa. 63. Act. 9.5.</note> And if God thus became man, (tooke our Ignominy and infirmities upon him) for us, ſhall wemen become beaſts to one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? deveſt our ſelves of this moſt noble part of humanity, and be ſo farre from Chriſtians, as not to be reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? in our tender compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to others, but like freeboo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Rifle and Rob them to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59507:34"/>
our ſelves, when they ſhould be objects of our pitty and releife; for there ought to be that harmony and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord amongſt us, as we ſhould endevour like one Inſtrument of many ſtrings to tune all our faculties, and affections into a ſweet agreement, that there might be no jarring amongſt our ſelves, nor diſagreement in our ſervice of God, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well ſet by one key, we may like two lutes (which by a holy ſympathy will both ſound when one is but ſtruck) the one feele the others motion, though moſt when like Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whoſe Pegs are wound up, their ſtrings ſcrued to the height, by any outward vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence they make the ſhril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt ſounds, according to that of the Apoſtle,<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 13.3</note> 
               <hi>Remember
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59507:35"/>
them in bonds, as bound,</hi> being our ſelves of the body; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when I am ſure, that if a Toe (the meaneſt and remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt member) be but trod upon, Chriſt our head feeles it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, our charitie muſt be exerciſed in cenſuring o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Actions; for ſo <hi>love ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth all things, beleeveth all things,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.</note> and ever takes them in the beſt ſence, is never ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, nor poſitive in judging them by their outward condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in that the Corne is as much thraſht as the ſtraw, the Gold as much tryed (though not waſted) in the fire as the Droſſe. Nay many times much more; for there may be a Rich <hi>Dives,</hi> whoſe Cups over-flow with wine, when poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> is glad to refreſh himſelfe with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59507:35"/>
Element of water;<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 16.</note> a good tree may appeare wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, blaſted, and dying with the violence of outward ſtormes, or recoyling of the ſap of Grace to the Root in ſome ſtronge temptation;<note n="*" place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.1, 2.</note> when the fruitleſſe bay tree is green, and flouriſhing, ſo as with the wiſe man we may ſay, none can judge of love, or hatred, by what is before him (of no mans ſpirituall condition by his temporall) in that all things ſublunary come alike to all. For it is not Gods diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of outward bleſſings, but our uſe of them, that makes the difference. And though the ſhadow of his wings be a ſhelter,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 63.7.</note> in the hot ſun-ſhine of Perſecution; none but a <hi>David</hi> can then truly rejoyce in it, and there finde comfort, and refreſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:59507:36"/>Thirdly, our charities are exerciſed by Afflictions, when we teach as well by example as Precept, in our cheerefull, innocent, and charitable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoing them. Thus Saint <hi>Paul</hi> propounds himſelfe a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne for us to tranſcribe,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.6.</note> that with thoſe in the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions we might follow the Lambe whereſoever he goeth, though not in equall paces, yet in ſlow motions,<note place="margin">Joh. 14.4</note> who thus ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to leave us an example (and he that was the way ſure beſt knew how to guide it) that we might follow his patterne at leaſt,<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 12.2.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Jo. 14.6.</note> if not commands; for <hi>Regis ad exemplum,</hi> the King is the great wheele in the State, that carries the inferiour ones with him; the examples of great men uſually having a compulſary power in them,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:59507:36"/>
even from a principle in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Thus one Deere leads the whole heard, one bird the flock, one<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> a congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And therefore we ought to carry the lanterne in the Poope, to let the light of our Actions ſtill ſhew the way we ſteere in the greateſt ſtormes to recover a happy haven, that other weather beaten Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers may by it know how to ride out a Tempeſt, and arrive the ſame port. Thus a dead man ſometimes makes a living Chriſtian, and propagates by ſuffering, the blood of the Martyres being the generative ſeed of the Church, <hi>Phoenix</hi> like one riſing out of the urne, and aſhes of the other, the effuſion of one mans blood being as it were the transfuſion of the ſame ſpirits into many,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59507:37"/>
or with <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> one ſoule animating (in a ſucceſſion) di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers bodies, ever gathering ſtrength under preſſures, with the Camomile growing beſt when moſt trod on, and with the Palme moſt ſpreading when oppreſſed with any waight. Thus God defects, and anatomizes ſome, in them to read a Lecture to all: and ſo truly makes our Croſſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Crowne of rejoycing to others,<note n="*" place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.4.5.</note> as the Apoſtle ſaith, and our Afflictions but like the ſhaking of a ripe flower, which by it ſheds ſeeds, from whence many more doe ſpring, and grow, till the hand of God doe pluck them to adorne his owne Garland with in heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> Fourtenthly, Gods hand upon us cals for ours upon our ſelves, humiliation as well as
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59507:37"/>
humility, and not with the worme turne againe upon him that treads upon us, but we muſt judge &amp; afflict our ſelves, and be moſt forward in a holy revenge to crucifie thoſe ſins, that moſt crucifie our Saviour, and by their death to give life to the contrary vertues, by our outward comportment ſhewing our inward affections, and not onely beare when God layes it on, but take up the Croſſe to Croſſe our ſelves, when our ſinnes, or Gods threatned judgements cals for it, not putting the evill day from us with joy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, eating of fleſh, and drinking of wine, (which is to be poſſeſſed with a ſtrange de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, if taken in exceſſe, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties caſting us into the water, and ſometimes into the fire)
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59507:38"/>
when God cals us to weeping and mourning,<note n="*" place="margin">Jſ. 22.12.13.</note> and baldneſſe, the true Emblems of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; not court our eyes with vaine objects, ſuffering them to be burning glaſſes of luſt to inflame the heart, when they ſhould be fountaines of teares to quench the inflamed wrath of God againſt us for our ſins, not feaſt to nouriſh, when we ſhould faſt to mortifie ſinne in us, not raviſh our ſenſes with harmonious Muſick, when our ſad conſort ſhould be made up of ſignes, and grones (the moſt melodious voyces for Gods quire, though harſh, and ſhrill in our eares) not gratifie our Palates by plundering all the Elements of their luxurious dainties, to furniſh our Tables, (and with the ewe tree roote our ſelves in the graves, and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59507:38"/>
ruines of others) when we ſhould come neereſt the invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Angels in their abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, not rock our ſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſleepe, and lethargy of ſin in Beds of Ivery, but tame our rebell luſts by watching, and holy vigilancy.<note n="*" place="margin">Amos. 6.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Joel. 2. Jſa. 1: Jam. 4.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor: 11.32.</note> For thus affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting our ſelves with rods, we ſhall avoyd Gods correcting us with ſcorpions, and make our loweſt deſcent here the ground of our Exaltation; Like that of Chriſt, who was therefore raiſed becauſe he humbled himſelfe to the greateſt depth of Ignominy, ſcorne, and ſelfe abaſement, even all degrees of Puniſhment, Paine, ſhame, and Death. And the ſervant you know, ſhould not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove his Lord, but (as he was) be made perfect through ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, which made <hi>Solomon</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:59507:39"/>
ſay,<note n="*" place="margin">Eccl. 7.</note> 
               <hi>that the houſe of mourning is better then that of mirth; for by the ſadneſſe of the countenance the heart is made better,</hi> whereas unſeaſonable or immoderate pleaſure like a ſurfet, is ever the mother of ſome diſeaſe, ſome grievous puniſhment. And if we once come not only to pleaſe but pride our ſelves in them (nay in our beſt graces; even the correcting our ſelves in thoſe exceſſes) like a gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greene in a joynt, it will cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the whole frame, and cannot but ruine us, that caſt the Angels out of Paradiſe it ſelfe. But if we caſt our ſelves downe before God, and like ſtarres the higher they riſe, ſtill leſſen in our owne eyes, he will raiſe us; for like the beſt mines, a Chriſtian the deeper and lower he is in the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59507:39"/>
earth, (in thoughts of morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and mortification) the richer; it being the vallies, not ſhelving hils that drink in (and ſo become faire and fruitefull with) the bleſſing from above. Nay it is <hi>the bruiſed reed, and ſmoaking flax,</hi> that God ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to preſerve<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 12.20.</note>, when with <hi>Hugo,</hi> Preſumption robs us of our God, and his protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, envy of our neighbours, and anger of our ſelves, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be againſt our ſelves, for then onely it turnes into ſelfe love.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, and moſt properly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> God ſends afflictions for the trial of our patience, in that it never appeares but under preſſures (though, if true, it is alwayes waiting upon God in habit and affections) and is the ſoules retiring roome in all
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59507:40"/>
diſtreſſes; a Mount Sion, <hi>which is not to be removed,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Jſa. 26.20 21. Pſa. 125.</note> 
               <hi>but ſtandeth faſt for ever (a).</hi> A peice of earth as the Spaniards ſay, however trod upon, and expoſed to iniuries, that is the laſt thing that triumphs over its enemies: A grace that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhewes beſt with the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amond, upon a darke foyle; a well drawne picture, whoſe ground-worke is ever laid in the ſaddeſt colours, and like the ſpangled canopy of heaven ever ſhines brighteſt when the curtaines are drawne, and the chamber hung with blacks in the moſt ſad and darkeſt night of temptation. Thus this Grace did ſhine cleereſt in the ſetting of the Sunne of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 21.10.</note> and his greateſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clips upon the croſſe, who did then <hi>poſſeſſe his ſoule in patience,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59507:40"/>
(b)</hi> when torne from his body by his paſſions, for thither it retired againſt the wrath of God, and malice of men, as to the heart ſconce, or fort Royall for ſecurity, which is never to be taken by famine, nor the aſſault of any enemy: In that patience (if pious) is ſo fortified (having the ſtrength of all the other graces, and God himſelfe to be its <hi>hiding place, ſtrength, ſheild,</hi> and <hi>deliverer</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 23 35.37.119.114.</note>, the rock upon which it is built) as it can never be overcome, nor want a rich harveſt for ſupply of proviſions, when moſt ſtraitened; for it can bring forth humble and peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent (though not repining) teares, which are ever a rich granary to the godly, in that God <hi>will feed them with the bread of teares,</hi> and (though it
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59507:41"/>
be but a thinne and penitenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all diet,) will make them as the ſtaffe of food to nouriſh and ſupport them, when all other refreſhments faile<note n="d" place="margin">Pſ. 42.13.80.5. Matt. 5.4. Luk. 6.21.</note>. And at laſt, when almoſt exhauſted, they have a voice and cry lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 6.</note> and have ſuch a char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſound, ſuch a powerfull oratory in them, as God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe cannot reſiſt it, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently approaches like a man of warre, and brings releife to ſtreightened and beſieged pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience. And if the batteries of the enemy ſhall not onely have deſtroyed and demoliſhed its towers, and turrets of orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but throwne downe all its upper roomes of ſtate and conveniency; Patience can lodge more ſafely and as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly upon the loweſt floore amongſt the rubbiſh and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59507:41"/>
ruines of a decaied greatneſſe; knowing that he cannot want the conveniency of any place, that hath God with him that fils all places, but chiefely makes his ſervants Priſon his Mantion to abide in with them (be it ſpoken in a pious ſence) and needs no rich Tapeſtries for State, but humility; no perfumes, but Prayes; no Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments but the Graces, no Crown but the Croſſe, though then he will turne our Croſſes into Crownes, our preſſures, into Praiſes, raviſhing us with Anthems of delight, compoſed of ſighes, and groanes.</p>
            <p>From all which conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if the feet of the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of Peace are beautifull, what welcome entertainment ought we to give Afflictions, which are the Heralds of it, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:59507:42"/>
are ſent but to force us to a Parly and accommodation with our God, and by depreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ſtuddies our advancement.<note n="*" place="margin">Luk 6 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3. Jam. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Nay let us be glad, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in them, when they are upon us; for when oppreſſed with ſinne, they are our Purge, Chriſts blood our Cordiall; and then though my Phiſitian come with a bitter potion, with fire to burne, and cauterize me, he is ſtill but an Enemy to my diſeaſe, not me, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he cure by a long or ſhort Diet.</p>
            <p>Yet in regard of the ſenſe of our weakneſſe, which will ſometimes ſay to us (perhaps as the Angell did to <hi>Ioſeph) Ariſe, take up thy young, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der babe,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 2.13.</note> (thy weak and new borne faith) <hi>and flye,</hi> we may ſeeke our own preſervation;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59507:42"/>
both pray, and indevour to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyd an approching perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or triall; For better a holy flight, then a preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtay, by which we tempt the Tempter. And this we have from Chriſt, both by precept and example; in that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us to Pray, <hi>Leade us not into Temptation,</hi> but <hi>when they perſecute you in one City, flie to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother;</hi> And did many times with draw himſelfe in the like caſe from the malice of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. For though we may not leape over the wall, or by any unjuſt meanes preſerve our ſelves, we may goe out of Priſon (from our troubles) when God open us a doore, and gives us an honeſt and faire opportunity, and not by a raſh boldneſſe provoke a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger (againſt all circumcellious
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59507:43"/>
whatſoever) for ſo <hi>Chriſt walked no more openly,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 11.54.</note> but ſaught ſanctuary, and ſafe quarter in the wilderneſſe, when he could not injoye it in the City, like a wiſe Pilot not ſplitting his veſſell on a Rock, when he can with a faire winde put into a harbour; accounting it rather murther, then Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome to attempt a danger, where it may lawfully be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyded; which made the God of all power flye from weake man,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.2.</note> and Saint <hi>Paule</hi> eſcape without ſinne,<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 9.25.</note> when <hi>Peter</hi> ſinned by his too much confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 16.26.</note> for God Almighty is ſo wiſe a Generall, as to keepe a reſerve, and not hazard all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one battle, but made <hi>Zoar Lots</hi> retreat from Sodome, and his deſtroying Angell. So as we muſt not with the Dolphin
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59507:43"/>
hunt the ſtorme, yet with a well poiſed zeale willingly, not wilfully bear it, when it comes, in a conformity to Chriſt, as a pledge of our filiation for his Glory, our ſanctification, and profit<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 8.29. Phil. 1.29. 1 Pet. 4.16. 1 Pet. 3.15</note>; for the beſt things here are but a dimme veſper of a more glorious feſtivall, and the time of injoying them but a poore halfe Holiday to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. And therefore let us, with the Apoſtles take joyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the loſſe of all for God,<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 4.41.</note> who wil then ſtrik a noon daies light into the ſaddeſt night-peece of Afflictions; turne our Gibbets, and places of executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into Triumphall Arches, and make us perſecute our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors more with our pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, then they can us with their torments. But that man, that will be his owne God (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:59507:44"/>
himſelfe by any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull meanes, or flye when Gods glory, or the Churches good commands his ſtay) is not as one ſaith, his owne man. Therefore lets us ſtill enjoy our ſelves by patience,<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> our brethren by Charity, and our God by faith, making every ſubmiſſive Act a Confeſſour (as the babes before they could ſpeake,) and our ſelves in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, and reſolution Martyrs, every light Affliction but like a rub to an overthrowne bowle, to helpe, not hinder us towards our marke: And then undergoing all for a good cauſe, it will ſave us, when we cannot ſave it (but muſt ſee the Arke taken by the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines, and the glory depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Iſrael)<note n="d" place="margin">1 Sam. 3.</note> if we ſuffer without murmuring, where
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59507:44"/>
we cannot act without ſinning, and dye when we cannot doe againſt our owne conſcience, or Gods commands; ſince God by it doth but take us into ſafe Garriſon from a bloody field<note n="e" place="margin">Act. 21.13.</note>; yet his Grapes muſt be thus preſſed before they yeeld the joy of gladneſſe to us; nor then, if we beare it not with Innocence, meekneſſe, and contentedneſſe For it is not the outward Act, but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Affections, and intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that makes a good and a happy man, and turnes the ſtake into his Theater the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly place of his joy, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:59507:45"/>
               <head>Of Jnnocence.</head>
               <p n="1">1. O Bleſſed Innocence, the perfection of the triumphant Saints, the beauty of Angels, the life of heaven, Image of God, nay God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, how art thou attainable here below, ſince thou onely inhabiteſt above? Yes, God in his humiliation, and becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sonne of man, made it deſcend with him both for our Imputation, and Imitation, that wee the children of men, might become the ſonnes of God. Sonnes both by Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſimilitude, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent him in likeneſſe, and Image; in perfection of parts, though not dimenſion, (as a
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59507:45"/>
childe a man in little) for wee muſt be innocent, as he was innocent, in quality, not equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of purity and holineſſe; for in Chriſt it was like water in the fountaine, cleane, and pure; in us, as in the ſtreame, terrene, and muddy; onely, we muſt draw our lines, and write as neere the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall as we can, even Chriſts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and tranſcribe that Primitive and true Copy of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence in an active and legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Character, that as he, ſo we may not be onely Innocent in ſufferings (Dovelike without all gall, and bitterneſſe) but ſuffer Innocently, as <hi>falſe, and yet true, as Dying, and behold we live,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 2 Cor. 4.6.</note> bleſſing our enemies, and praying with Saint <hi>Steven</hi> for our perſecutors, ever over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming evill with good turnes
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59507:46"/>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Pro. 26.32.19.11.</note> and accounting it the greateſt victory to overcome, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer one's ſelfe. For thus ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering according to the will of God, and committing our ſelves to him in well doing, as into the hands of a faithfull Creatour,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.19.</note> he will doe well for us, and preſerve us by his power unto ſalvation,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.5</note> and turne our white robe of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency here, (though full of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſpots) into an immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late one of glory.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Meekeneſſe is a calme and quiet temper of the ſoule, and (as walls and bulwarkes to a City)<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 25.28.</note> defends the man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt anger, and all ſuch paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions (which are but a kinde of ſhort madneſſe) that would conquer reaſon, and ſo turne the man out of doores, out of himſelfe; nay if this grace be
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:59507:46"/>
wanting, it opens a breach for the enemy to enter, and not only carri's us captive from our ſelves, but our God too, who is not to be found in the ſtorm, nor earthquake, but in the ſtill calme, and gentle voice, (as to <hi>Elias</hi>) whereas a meek man is like the bole or great branches of a Tree, not to be ſhaken by the greateſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts; thus a Heathen, Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas could eſteeme it, when he would never revenge an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury (if angry) but upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. So <hi>Socrates,</hi> when <hi>Xantippe</hi> threw water in his face, made no anſwer, but that after a ſtorme raine was ſeaſonable, and that he ſaw the ſame face upon all events. And ſhall they in this be more then men, and we Chriſtians leſſe then ſome beaſts? O no.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:59507:47"/>
Let us by this temper beare all things without diſturbance (afflictions from God, Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries from men) for like milke it will ſooneſt quench wilde-fire, In that <hi>a ſoft anſwer,</hi> as Solomon ſaith, <hi>endeth ſtrife:</hi> and like Mouſe are though it be ſilken in the handling, can with its juyce cut the hardeſt Iron, mollifie and ſoften the moſt ſtony heart, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come both God and man; when all paſſions if unboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, like the evening fogs in ſome Countries, prove dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, diſcolour and taint the veſſels they are in, like the worſt poiſons; which made the Lion of the tribe of Juda ſuffer like a Lambe (the Lambe of God.) And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the print of that Seale at leaſt, let meekeneſſe and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59507:47"/>
ſoftneſſe of ſpirit be ſtampt upon all our actions, that we may not become our owne tormentors. And</p>
               <p n="1">1. Towards God, for when he afflicts, ſilence is our beſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulation, dumbneſſe our beſt oratory. And thus <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> a man after Gods owne heart framed his<note n="a" place="margin">Pſ. 37.7.</note>; or if we ſay any thing, let not our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe (as in hot feavers) break out at our lips in any impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but with good <hi>Ely</hi> in an humble ſubmiſſion, confeſſe it is the Lord, <hi>Let him doe what ſeemeth him good</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">1 Sam. 3.28.</note>, for the <hi>recipe</hi> and medicine muſt be wholeſome however ſharpe, if God be the Phyſitian.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Towards our Enemies, and perſecutors, knowing it is the glory of a man to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come injuries, and becauſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59507:48"/>
the wrath of man worketh not not the will of God;<note n="*" place="margin">Jam. 1.</note> it is the will of God to puniſh the fury and wrath of man, but contrarily to reward him for ſufferings: many times ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king our bittereſt cup, even death it ſelfe, but a mornings draught to Eternity, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to draw our enemies from admiration to the love and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itation of us, and makes the conquerer a captive to the conquered, teaching them the way to happineſſe by our unhappineſſe; rectifies the Crooked line by the ſtraight, their cruelty in impoſing by our meekneſſe in ſuffering; or elſe makes us take a godly, though unwilling revenge, by heaping coales of fire on their heads, and inflaming the very flames of hell againſt them;
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59507:48"/>
however meekneſſe will be our ornament.<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 3.4. James 1.20.</note> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 25.28.</note> No Jewell being ſo pretious in the eyes of God, nor any thing raiſing us ſo much above the ſphere of man, in that it makes us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a miracle of wonder to others, and is to our ſelves an earneſt of future bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to which all preſent feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city is but as a drop to the Ocean, a ſparke to the whole Element of fire; yet, let us from hence learne not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, but regulate our paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. For as we may be angry, and not ſinne in it; ſo in ſome caſes we may ſinne in not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing angry for God;<note n="*" place="margin">Eph. 4 26</note> Anger, and many other paſſions being like ſome ſtarres,<note n="*" place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 22.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9.29.</note> good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill onely in regard of their conjunction.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Contendedneſſe, is a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59507:49"/>
that makes a man Maſter of his owne happineſſe, the ſtorehouſe of his own wealth, which made <hi>cyneas</hi> wiſh <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> to enjoy his preſent comforts, without ſtaying for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the Romans, &amp; Affri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans; and ſets him above the maſtery of Fortune, knowing it is from within, not without that muſt make him rich; for with Plutarkes mule, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented man can be pleaſed to want his golden carriage, knowing that all worldly things are but as a waite to ſlow us in our journey to heaven; the greateſt preferments but glorious ſervitudes, and rich fetters, which made <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> ſay, his victories were enough to undoe the Conquerour, in that what is got by power is commonly kept with care and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:59507:49"/>
hazard; eſpecially, if like flies that moſt commonly ſuck their nutriment from wounds and ſores, we live upon the blood and teares of other men. And if a heathen could be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of ſuch a pious moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let us make it the center of our deſires, as moſt diffuſive of equall Juſtice to all, and moſt uniting, and reconciling all extreames from a middle ſymbolizing with both; and if like a ſtill we thus keep our ſelves in a moderate temper, we ſhall willingly want with ſubmiſſion, what we cannot get by lawfull meanes, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that all things in this world (even life it ſelfe) are but the dreſſe, and ſhadowes of good, when vertue onely, and a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py death brings the refined part. But admit there were
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:59507:50"/>
true happineſſe in injoying the beſt coloured dirt, or any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſplendid greatnes, yet he that deſires no more then he hath, hath in that more then any other can injoy in having their deſires in all things elſe. For there, as in a dropſie, drinking doth but increaſe thirſt, and deſire being infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite (in reſpect of the bounded joyes of this world) hath ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent not preſent felicity for its object, and is ſo farre here from being ſatisfyed, that the worldly mans happineſſe doth but increaſe his Trouble, like <hi>Alexanders,</hi> whoſe heart inlarged with his poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions (ſo as one world could not fill it) but loſt his felicity in that he had wonne, by wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for another that he might conquer, whereas contented
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:59507:50"/>
poverty is a happy Fortune (becauſe it fixeth our reſtleſſe deſires;) yet then we may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert it with <hi>Seneca,</hi> and ſay, It is not poverty, if it be content; how much more therefore ſhould wee Chriſtians learne with Saint <hi>Paul, in what condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſoever we are,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 4.</note> to center in a ſubmiſſive ſatisfaction, taking no dividing, diſtracting thoughts, and care for any thing, no not for food, and rayment,<note n="*" place="margin">Matt. 6.</note> though of all things elſe they intitle themſelves to our Aſſiduity, and diligence in their obteyning. But let us caſt our burden, and care upon God, for he beareth the one, and is ever mindfull of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 37.55.22. 1 Pet. 5.7.</note> Nay he hath promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that if we firſt <hi>ſeeke the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, and the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof, all theſe things
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:59507:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſhall be added,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 6.33.</note> as an over waight to us, added, not given, becauſe of no great worth nor value with a pious man, if we caſt our ſelves upon him in a holy recumbency, and fiduciall confidence for the reſt.<note n="b" place="margin">Pſ. 34. Jſa. 26.</note> A moſt holy thirſt or way to want nothing neceſſary for us, yet here we muſt onely leave the event to God, not omit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lawfull and moderate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour on our parts, as ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient to his providence, which ordinarily doth not carry us from one extreame to another but by middle wayes; for though he provides our daily bread, he gives it onely to them, that aske, and labour for it;<note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.8.</note> but when our actions as well as our tongues, put forth their voyce they cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud in the eares of God,<note n="*" place="margin">Mal. 3.</note> and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:59507:51"/>
never miſſe of a bleſſing; for as he that gives us life, cannot want meanes to continue it (in that he can make the rich mans barne the poore mans maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zine) ſo by giving one, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes our debter for the reſt, <hi>Deus donando debet,</hi> if wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell not our title by diſtruſt; Gods preſent benefits, being ingagements to future mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, like <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> one having a hand upon the others heel, they come into the world as twins.</p>
               <p>Nay, it were the greateſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme, and infidelity in the world to thinke (if we be not wanting to our ſelves) that God either can or will let us want any thing that is good,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> when to convince us, he doth not onely ſend us to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, but to his unexampled
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:59507:52"/>
goodneſſe, even towards his irrationall creatures; <hi>to the lilie of the field, which</hi> ſaith he, <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpins,</hi> nor takes paines; <hi>to the fowles of the ayre, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſow nor reape;</hi> and ſhall not we aske as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother place ſayes of Oxen, doth God take this care of flowers, birds &amp; beaſts, and ſhall he not much more provide for man, for whoſe uſe, ſervice, and delight, thoſe creatures were made? Nay, ſhould we want bread, yet we ſhall not want life; for man of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures lives not by bread onely, but by the bleſſing of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. For thus God can give forty dayes ſuſtenance in one ſmall refreſhment as to <hi>Elias,</hi> and put leanneſſe into the ſoules of thoſe that are daily fed with quailes, and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59507:52"/>
manna; for his children uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fare beſt upon a hard diet, (like many birds that grow fatteſt in ſharpeſt and moſt biting weather) and with poor <hi>Lazarus</hi> get more health, and ſtrength from <hi>Dives</hi> his crums, (the dogs ordinary) then the other from all his full diſhes; and with the Nightingale ſings moſt ſweetly, when the thorne is againſt her breaſt, (moſt pricked, and ſtung by any mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery,) like <hi>Paul,</hi> &amp; <hi>Silas</hi> in their chaines, nay, ſuch is Gods goodneſſe to us, that if naturall bowels faile, he will ſtill take care of us; as of thoſe birds that expoſe their young ones as ſoone as hatched, to a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle for preſervation,<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 12.24.</note> and will fill our mouthes with a ſweet dew or ſomething nutritive from heaven, if we open them
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:59507:53"/>
that way to call upon him in Prayer<note n="*" place="margin">Job. 38.41. Pſ. 147.9.</note> (ſo the naturaliſts) whereas the affluence of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bleſſings many times (like the grovling ſow to her young ones) kils us with abundance. And this, as one obſerves, made the Raven (that was unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to her owne <hi>Elias</hi> his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer in his diſteſſe, as a return of gratitude to God, for nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing up her young one with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out her owne breaſt: but I rather draw this concluſion from it, that God who made the moſt unnaturall creature in the world ſo ſerviceable, and compaſſionate towards man in his diſtreſſe, neither can, nor ever will want wayes and meanes to releive us, if our eyes be upon him (with good <hi>Iehoſophat</hi> when ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with deſtruction) and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59507:53"/>
with <hi>Iob,</hi> by making our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in his mercies out live death it ſelfe. For certainly, God can never caſt them out of his protection, that thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon his providence, but will allow for neceſſity, though not for outward bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, and inſteed of the artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall glittering beauties of the world, will cloth them with the Lilies whitenes (Innocency here as an under garment) till they be clothed upon with glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hereafter. And therefore ſince our heavenly Father knowes better what is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for us, then we for our ſelves, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpenſes it to us moſt ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably, let us ſubmit to every condition, and rather expect a bleſſing upon our poverty, then deſire his outward ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:59507:54"/>
with a curſe;<note n="*" place="margin">Pſa. 78.</note> for God loves meaſure in all things, and gives to every living crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as they have need, and would not have the heart of man more unreaſonable then the unreaſonable ſea (the moſt unquiet of all the Elements) but keep it ſelfe within fit bounds, and limits; for as juſt proportion of humors in the body, an equall poiſe of power in the ſtate (betweene ſupreame power, and common intereſt) an even mixture of the elements, preſerves the whole univerſe, ſo with <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> neither to deſire poverty, nor riches, but to acquieſce in what God pleaſes to ſhew his love in to us, is the middle and happy temper of a Chriſtian, &amp; that which makes him moſt enjoy himſelfe in all conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:59507:54"/>
and moſt perſevering in holineſſe. Therefore let us moderate our ſelves in our deſires toward the things of this life,<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 6. 1 Tim 6. Prov. 30. Heb. 2.</note> ever looking beyond the preſent condition to the future event, and with Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> (ſeeing one going to execution with a croud of attendants along the moſt faire and beautifull ſtreets, and another without the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance or company of a friend, paſſing the moſt nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, troubleſome and unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant lanes to a happy marriage bed) cry out, <hi>Non qua, ſed quo, non via, ſed finis;</hi> and thinke our ſelves ſafer in ſhipwrack (God being our Pilote) then the wicked can be in the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of their happineſſe,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 37. Eccl. 9.</note> in that it cannot goe ill with the righteous when the <hi>wicked
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:59507:55"/>
muſt periſh;</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Eccleſ. 8. Job. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Eccleſ. 2. Pſal. 34. 1 Pet. 3.4. 2 Cor. 1.4.6.</note> nay for our fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comfort we ſhall not live altogether upon expectation, depend upon reverſions, and have our wages deferred, for Godlineſſe is great gaine, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>the Promiſes both of this lif, and that to come,</hi> even preſent happineſſe in the moſt unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py outward condition, in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, wants, neceſſities, and death it ſelfe; for though the man that is earthly, as well as earth, lookes upon them in a multiplying glaſſe of ſence, and Perſpective of Fancy, and by it apprehends them more greater, and fuller of horrour, then they are in themſelves (and ſo becomes his owne wracke, and tormenter) the good Chriſtian, conſidering the leaſt benefit he injoyes, a mercy and bleſſing, every evill
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:59507:55"/>
he wants, a favour and indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; when many better then he, wants what he poſſeſſeth, and ſuffers under greater miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that he better merits; finds in this vale of miſery ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch wels to refreſh at, and can by Faith (which eaſily workes ſuch miracles) unmask the ſatyre, unſting the viper, and turne the ſeeming evils of this world into a reall good; for their vizard being once off, their venome out, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left to affright us, but many times they worke for our advantage, even in regard of preſent felicity, by want making us become rich, and by an holy chymiſtry turning all thoſe Irons that enter into our ſoules into golden ſcepters (in token of our conqueſt over our affections) emblemd by
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:59507:56"/>
the woman in the wilderneſſe, who then, and in that ſad and ſolitary condition, tramples upon the moone, all terrene things: for when one depth calleth upon another, our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery upon Gods mercy,<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 9. Dan. 9. Job. 13.10 Jer. 9.28. Jſa. 1.26.43. Jam. 4.8.10. Exod. 34. Pſal. 103.</note> he is ſo delighted with himſelfe in the exerciſe of that attribute, that he makes it at it were his darling, and the child of his nature,<note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.3.</note> (as Chriſt is the ſonne of his perſon) exalting it above all his workes, (nay and ours too, workes of ſinne to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, and deſtroy them) and to turne our Egyptian darkneſſe and ſervitude into a Goſhen, giving us for outward afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons inward joyes; for earthly loſſes, true and laſting delights; ſatisfaction in poverty, when many are poor, when richeſt; a heart not to deſire, which is
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:59507:56"/>
more then we can deſire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides: and drawing more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe from this dry Ciſterne, then <hi>Tantalus</hi> when in the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to the mouth, a holy rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, gaining by loſſe, and loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by gaine, an improving of our joy a hundred fold with perſecutions by loſing our goods;<note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 10. Marke 10. Job. 31.</note> in regard of inward peace, and complacency; the iſſue; and crown that followes it, if we can but learne with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> equally to want, and abound, in what condition ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever to be content,<note n="*" place="margin">Ph. 4. Prov. 1.14.13.7.</note> and by it make afflictions become a reall lye, &amp; our ſelvs a holy paradox when in having nothing we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy all things.<note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.</note> For if God be Chriſts, and Chriſt be ours, as the Apoſtle argueth, we have in him, as ſpring, and fountaine all other joyes, and comforts,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:59507:57"/>
that are but derivative from him; and in their ſeverall ſtreames communicated to us, and need looke no farther then to him for ſupply of all things fit for our condition. And therefore it is good to truſt, and waite with <hi>David</hi> for his ſalvation, who can make our priſon a Palace, our death a life, our hell here a heaven in regard of inward comforts; if in the dampe of affliction, (when our candle burnes dimme by our being too much undergrown in our affections) we make haſte to be drawn up, and ſet our converſations for heaven, and heavenly objects.</p>
               <p>But admit that with afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons God gives not that bleſſing in this life, ſo as in all the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell of our ſoules add ſharpeſt throws we cannot be delivered
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:59507:57"/>
of this promiſed ſeed, and nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous iſſue of happy fruits, (the effects, and productions of Gods grace, and goodneſſe to us), but when the Children are come to the birth, we want ſtrength to bring forth, ſo that with <hi>Phineas</hi> his wife,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Sam. 4.</note> we miſcarry in our Pangs, and looſe our lives, before our weake, though true, faith, and feeble midwife patience can deliver us of thoſe expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed joyes: yet then (and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver till then) we begin to live: the Act of our conſcientious death, for Chriſt, and a good cauſe, being our crowne of life (deferred onely becauſe we ſought it not as we ſhould, not loſt) our inthroneing,<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 2.</note> and inauguration in immortality, if we perſevere in a patient, pious, and humble comport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:59507:58"/>
in our ſufferings; for it is not our reſiſting (though to ſome drops of blood, if we make a diſhonourable retreat, but keeping the field dead, if not alive, that inables, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titles us to the Gardland, and Trophies of victory, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, who will ſwallow up the victory of the grave, and make it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the grave of its own vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, by giving up all its ſlain, and becoming a ſlave to its captives; for he that makes the greene Tree become dry, (he that thinkes himſelfe full of ſappe; and life to faide and dye) will make the dead, and withered one to ſpring againe, and flouriſh;<note n="*" place="margin">Iſ. 17.24.</note> nay, with <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deons,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Jug, 7.</note> till theſe earthen Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of our bodies are daſhed in peeces, the lampe of our
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:59507:58"/>
ſoules will never ſhine cleere, but then God reaſſuming them from the aſhes of their cold urnes, will make them as ſoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, in which their ſoules ſhall in endleſſe glory burne; And therefore, though God have his furnace, it is but to melt and refine us, to new caſt, and ſtampe us with his own Image, and make us, currant money for heaven, which is the true end of (as it puts an end to) all the Afflictions of the godly,<note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.4, 6.</note> and for ſowing in teares here, makes us reape joy,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 3.4</note> if we are not harder and more rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous againſt Gods rod,<note n="*" place="margin">Eccl. 7.</note> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 5. Pſ. 126.6.</note> then the flinty Rock was to <hi>Moſes</hi> (where fire rather then water was to be expected). Yet let us be Flints too in our inwards, ever keeping a virtuall fire, and zeale to Gods glory, to purge
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:59507:59"/>
us from all droſſe, and ſinne: for without it none ſhall enter into Paradice, nor be made heires of immortall glory.<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 6. Rev. 22.</note> So as you ſee our natures had need every way to be wrought upon; we are ſuch a maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peece of perverſneſſe, ſuch mettle as will not take impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from ſoft meanes, but muſt have the rough hammer and Axe of Afflictions to hew, and faſhion us, though like the ſunne beames they worke according to their object, melting wax, and hardening Clay, winning upon the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but obdurating the wicked, as the hammer the Anvill; and this makes God ſometimes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, that he might not be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with us, lightning before he thunders, warning before he wounds,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſ. 7.</note> afflicting here to
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:59507:59"/>
take away ſinne,<note n="*" place="margin">Iſ. 27.2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Jer. 4, 5.</note> that by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in ſinne we might not be everlaſtingly afflicted. And becauſe proſperity makes us unproſperous (in that we are naturally prone to turne Gods bleſſings into curſes,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſ. 69.106. Mal. 1.2.9 Pro. 1.31</note> and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver cry, <hi>Lord ſave us, we periſh,</hi> but with the Diſciples in a ſtorme,<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 8.24.27. Luke 8.</note>) God raiſes Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts amongſt us that (with <hi>Ionas,</hi> and the Marriners) may force us to call upon our God; for then are we onely ſaved, when we thinke our ſelves neereſt drowning,<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and may ſay with the Philoſopher, <hi>Perijſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem, niſi periiſſem,</hi> ſo as wee ought to be contented in all eſtates. Thus the dead wombe of <hi>Sarah</hi> will conceive, and bring forth an <hi>Iſaac</hi> of comfort, our winter dying blaſted condition will ſpring,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:59507:60"/>
and revive in death, and make it better in the wiſe mans opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, then birth,<note n="*" place="margin">Job. 5. Eccl. 7 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ob. 14.19.</note> in that it changes our habitation, earth for heaven, and extinguiſheth our rent here (feares, and teares) giving garments of gladneſſe for thoſe of heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for finite ſorrowes, joyes beyond Arithmetick to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber;<note place="margin">Iſ. 61. Cor. 7.6.</note> and in our paſſage over this red Sea will be both our way, and ſupport; never lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any burden upon us but lending his own ſhoulder to it, with the temptation ever gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the iſſue,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 10 3. Heb. 12.</note> and like a good Gardiner never cuts his Roſe buſh, but to render its flowers more ſweet, and floriſhing; like a good Phyſitian never lets us blood, but to cure our Tym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Pride, dropſie of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe, or the like, and
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:59507:60"/>
never tempts but only for tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, not ſeduction, nor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawes himſelfe, but to make us the better value his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and favours (contraries being the beſt comments upon one another) yet let us ever pray againſt this laſt as moſt dangerous, but ſtill rely upon him; never letting goe our Anchor, which will in the end, above, beyond, nay without meanes ſave us;<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 43. Pſa. 91. Ph. 2.4.</note> for if the Potter will not let his veſſell continue in the fire to deſtroy, but lute and fix it, the carrier not overload his beaſt, God much more remembring how weake we are built, and our foundations to be but duſt,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſa. 103</note> will weigh out his preſſures to our abilities, ſhortning our paines, or inlarging our pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, making all things to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:59507:61"/>
worke for our good;<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> the lines how contrary ſoever drawne to center in our happineſſe; and though in miſery we thinke our time ſtands ſtill, like <hi>Ioſhuahs</hi> ſunne; it then hath wings, upon which we ſoare towards heaven. Nay, God will not onely worke thus for us,<note n="*" place="margin">Ph. 2.13. Iſa. 26.12. Heb. 8.10. Eph. 1. Gal. 2.20.</note> but in us, by us, and upon us what he commands from us, filing us to make and forme us veſſels for his temple, hewing and ſquaring us, as timber for his Sanctuary, hammering our ſtony hearts for his ſpirituall building, ſmoothing and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing us for beauty and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament, and to ſhew his own reſemblance, and Image in us, when he in any of theſe wayes reflects upon us. But to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, God takes that care of us in all things as nothing can
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:59507:61"/>
hurt us, no temptation on the right nor left hand ſhall ever finally prevaile againſt us, but God will turne our deepeſt ſorrowes into our higheſt joyes, ſo as if in the fire of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like miſeries, (our homebred diſſentions which like <hi>Samſons</hi> Foxes devour all before them) the inward warmth of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, burnings of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, heat of zeale to Gods houſe or glory, doe as from a limbeck diſtill ſome heavenly drops from our eyes, turn our laughter into mourning, and make us raine upwards, that very trouble will improve to happineſſe, and thoſe drops turne into the water of life to us, and being kept in Gods bottle<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 58.</note> will fall downe againe upon us in refreſhing dewes to allay our greateſt inward
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:59507:62"/>
ſtormes; nay they are in Gods booke to waſh out our ſinnes, that ſhould be there regiſtred againſt us (yet onely as a meanes of obtaining mercy, not from any intrinſick worth) and out of our conſciences the blackeſt Characters of acted tranſgreſſions. Nay, theſe eye Jewels, or pearles in the eyes, falling from them will ſo cleer the ſight, as we ſhall diſcern the glittering vanities of this life to be but meer ſhadowes, ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing meteors, nothing but <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and vexation of ſpirit,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Eccl. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and not fall in love with that face that will not ſtay to be ſaluted, but rather ſee beauty in the blackemore; love the wrinkles, and blemiſhes that the trueſt picture of miſery (man under the Torrid Zone of Gods Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly diſpleaſure) can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent;
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:59507:62"/>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Iſay. 53.</note> for ſo we may eſpouſe an abiding happineſſe, and have eternity for joynture ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon us.<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 14.22.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore let us with patience runne the race (how rugged, and difficult ſoever we finde the way) <hi>looking to Ieſus, the Author and finiſher of our faith,</hi> that <hi>with him,</hi> and for him, <hi>we may endure the Croſſe, deſpiſe the ſhame</hi> for <hi>the joy ſet before</hi> us.<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> For <hi>ſuffering with him, we ſhall aſſuredly</hi> be <hi>glorified together,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 8.17, 18.</note> he ſhining like the ſune, and fountaine of light, we like leſſer ſtars bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing our luſtre from him, (being for ever fixt in the ſame Orbe) without either waine or Ecclips, injoying per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall day without night, joy without ſorrow, ſatisfaction without ſatiety, a happy eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:59507:63"/>
an eternall felicity, heaven being the only Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus above the meteors, and ſtormes <hi>of this world</hi> which for its inconſtancy is in the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> Emblemd by a Sea, and that of glaſſe, for its frailty, and brittleneſſe; in its forme circular, and moving to ſhew the inconſtancy of all things in it; its matter fading, vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and dying; to teach us the periſhableneſſe, and certaine mortality of all its beauties: for as the Father is, ſuch are the Children, all but empty glories; nay man himſelfe, the Maſter peece of nature, and comprehenſion of all other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and perfections, cloſe bound up in a little volume (if we looke into his materials, the weakneſſe and ſhort conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of the building) we can
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:59507:63"/>
account but as a vapour, a ſhadow, a bubble, that ſoone vaniſheth; a walking peece of earth, a well glazed pitcher, ſoone broken; a heap of ruine, rather then a faire ſtructure, and in his greateſt perfections a cipher or nothing. In that honour is but a blaze, or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teor, many times made up of the baſeſt matter; a treaſure without lock or key, more in the power of another, then the owner; riches but Gold; Gold, but a well coloured peece of dirt, which againſt nature, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then ſtay to make us hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, will (though a dull, and heavy element) take wings, and flye away; fame a hollow Eccho, beauty a well glazed pitcher, or fading flower, friendſhip a dying happineſſe, joy but folly, mirth a ſhort
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:59507:64"/>
madneſſe; all things in their longeſt continuance, but a ſound or flaſh of lightning, that dyes as ſoone as borne; a dim glaſſe, darke reſemblance, or apparition of future happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: for in the making of this goodly frame, (this out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>building or ſuburbs of heaven) as in a little note-booke, God onely writ in ſhort and ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible Characters (drew in modell or little) thoſe ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, inutterable raviſhing glories, that ſhall be revealed when the ſcene is to be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the curtaine drawne, the vaile of our ſoules (our bodies) done away, even ſuch as our cripled fancy, our imped and pinnioned imaginations cannot ſoare to, and therefore with a ſilent admiration, a blindneſſe occaſioned by ſeeing the luſtre
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:59507:64"/>
of many ſuns at once, let us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to enter that immence, infinite bleſſedneſſe (by faith) that cannot now enter into us (into our finite capacities) and begin our heaven in our holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the true way, approach, and gate to happineſſe: and from inward principles be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in our outward ſufferings for the name or cauſe of Jeſus,<note place="margin">Act. 20.</note> and ſo turne our enemies pitty at our preſſures into wonder at our patience, and our pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence into an everlaſting fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of bleſſedneſſe, and ſeale (if Gods honour require it, and our Countries good) to that truth by our deaths, we have made profeſſion of in lives<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 2.12.</note> ſuffering all evill or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, rather then commit any the leaſt evill of ſinne; for ſuch a temper of the ſoule (when
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:59507:65"/>
in the loweſt center of miſery) will like fire to fewell turne all into it ſelfe, into ſatisfaction, if not complacency, and with the wood in <hi>Exodus</hi> will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert theſe bitter waters into ſweet and refreſhing ſprings. But if our weake faith doth not worke ſuch miracles,<note place="margin">Exo. 15.25.</note> let not our ſoules be vexed, nor diſquieted within us, but truſt in God, (as well for the reſurrection of our joyes here, as of our bodies hereafter) who is the helpe of our counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and our God,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſa. 42.43.</note> and having received preſſe mony (paſt favours, which are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes pledges of future mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies) let us waite upon God, fight unto death, and not quit our colours for want of pay here, but expect our triumphs hereafter; when the enemy,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:59507:65"/>
ſinne, and death are totally vanquiſhed; and in the meane time, (like Cloth in the fullers hand which muſt be thorowly whited, and dreſſed to make up thoſe robes of ſtate, (the innocency of the Saints) we muſt be for ever adorned with hereafter) let us yeeld our ſelves to be trampled on, and rinſed in ſeverall waters (many troubles) ſtill fearing that if the deluge of Affliction once begin to fall, or abate, a worſe ſlime of ſinne will co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the face of our earthly hearts, and we for ever may ſtick faſt in that mire, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out water to cleanſe us, if the fountaines opened to <hi>Iuda,</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> for uncleaneſſe be ſtopt againſt us, and then if the Baits of ſinne, delights of the world carry us along in
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:59507:66"/>
thoſe ſoft and boggy wayes, and ſinke us deeper; how ever their entertainments are ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the preſent with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, we ſhall ever finde the Bees ſting in their taile; their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion will be bitterneſſe; and if our tenderneſſe ſhrinkes at the prickling of Afflictions here, how ſhall we endure the wrack hereafter? if not the ſparkes of divine diſpleaſure, how the flames of hell fire for ever, and ever?</p>
               <p>Now to prevent this miſery, which is as immortal, as the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the body as the ſoule, the ſoule as God himſelfe; let us take lawfull pleaſures here, (when God allowes them) but not ſuffer them to take us, yet ſometimes pleaſe our ſelves in the want of pleaſure it ſelfe<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 7.29.31.</note>; for what we ſow in weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:59507:66"/>
ſhall riſe in power<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> nay to Glory — nay in Glory; for as all Joyes here flow into the joyes of Heaven (as rivers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sea) ſo the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chriſtian ſhall not looſe his in death. But his ſoule aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoon as out of his body, ſhall only goe from one Heaven to an other; for the way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is Heaven, ſo that as the Angels did not deveſt Heaven in coming to us, good ſoules do inveſt Heaven in going to them, the true joy that a <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus,</hi> (a ſoule in union with God and Chriſt) apprehends here,<note place="margin">Joh 14.16</note> being that none can take from him. For as one ſaith wittily, crowd Heaven into a Map, its two Hemiſpheres are made up of joy and glory, joy uſhering in glory, ſo that in the anguiſh of death, agony of
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:59507:67"/>
diſſolution, viſion of horror, nay ſight of hell it ſelfe, I ſhall ſee the face of God; and all theſe will be, but as Glaſſes that collect, and reflect his ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing rayes upon me, adding joy to joy, and glory to both, and exchange for <hi>a great bubble</hi> (blowne out with an eaſie breath; for that childe, and darling of time, <hi>antiquity in blood,</hi> for <hi>an empty aery title,</hi> which is innobled onely by action, and retaines nothing but the wax fit for any labell, (if wanting the ſtamp of true piety and worth.) for the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſound of fame,) a crowne that can never be loſt for good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and vertue will reflect a brave luſtre upon the memory of a dead, as well as upon the perſon of a living Saint; a gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant eccho of praiſe when
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:59507:67"/>
dead, for his praiſing of God, when living: and though, as one ſaith, envy may ſometimes miſt the glaſſe of Reputation, ſo that it ſhall not report a cleere light, yet at the laſt judgement it will reverberate truly, and we ſhall ſhine in a ſphere all brightneſſe, and be known by a tranſparent light on every ſide, what we were here, what we are in heaven, to the glory of God, joy of the Saints, ſhame and deriſion of of our enemies. So great is the convictive Majeſty of goodneſſe in the beames of the ſetting ſunne, and though the higheſt perfection of the ſoule, the moſt ſublimed part of man here is full of imperfections, blemiſhes, and dying beauties, which doe rather hide, then ſhew the glory of a ſanctified
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:59507:68"/>
ſpirit, or the true Image of God drawn in little there; yet this way of taking God into us is our onely way of being taken into God, and to make him our ſheild, and exceeding great reward,<note place="margin">Gen. 5.</note> our defence here, and Crowne hereafter, when our Candles ſhall be put out in our earthen ſockets, our lofty blowne bladders empty them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of breath, and we ſleepe in death, a darke Gallery, or ſhady walke onely leading be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two lives the period and Omega of the earthly mans happineſſe, the Alpha, and beginning of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans bleſſedneſſe, the higheſt ſtep to honour, and birth day to eternity, where we ſhall for ever injoy day without night, ſatisfaction without ſatiety, a tranquill happineſſe in a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:59507:68"/>
tranquillity, eternall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe in a bleſſed eternity. So be it, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <p>GEntle Reader, though naturally men love the iſſue of their braines more then of their bodies (in that they are many times longer lived; more true and laſting records of the innobled ſoules they derive their pedigree from; then the other) yet the authour of this little worke choſe rather to be forgotten, then remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred by a peece; that (if examined by a cleer and open light) will repreſent him with ſo many errours and ill drawn features to the world, and deſigned it one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for himſelfe and his; but truly a civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to the law of friendſhip (where deſires are commands) and the conſideration of its uſefulneſſe in regard of the unhappy Harmony betweene its ſubject and theſe times made me firſt lend (and now
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:59507:69"/>
ſend it) abroad, and give it line beyond its authours intention, though not liberty to goe but whether my hand directs; for I have onely Printed a few Coppies to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie ſome private importunities; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if thou be one of that number, its failings are now mine and thine, and ſo intitle themſelves to your forgiveneſſe, which is the humble requeſt of thine in all affection.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:59507:69"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
